SQL Online Transaction
Processing. Who's down?
You down with OLTP?
Who's down with OLTP?
Back
to your final module
before you take exam one.
Today we're going to cover Online
Transaction Processing or OLTP.
OLTP represents the everyday
transactions that you would
make using SQL Server. For
instance, you register for
a course, or you drop a
course, you change your major,
you get admitted to the hospital,
or you make a purchase. All
of these are handled through
online transaction processing.
The other type of OL is
considered OLAP, Online Analytical
Processing, and that's where
you tend to use the data to make
decisions related to trends and
decision-making and so forth.
In this module, we will focus
on primarily the update and the
alter table. We've covered the insert
statement, the create statement,
the delete statement, drop table,
truncate in the prior module.
So we'll focus primarily on
the update and the alter table.
Although this is a shorter module,
it's fairly heavily weighted on
the exam. 30% of your exam is
based on coding questions. Those
coding questions would derive
from last module on create, table,
insert, into, drop,
truncate, and delete. And the
remainder of the coding
questions would be related to the
alter table update statements
that we'll cover today.
We'll first take a look at the
update statement. It's considered
a DML, data manipulation language,
because it's intended to fix or
update or make a change to generally
a single row. And so that's
why it's considered to be a DML.
I've got a short intro to the
update statement, and as you watch
this brief interview on memories,
the idea is Bob Mills growing older,
and my hair changes colors, and
you'll notice in the video the
update statement contains three
lines of statement, the final
one being the where clause. In
a real-world situation, I'd
use an A number or a social
security number, something that
uniquely identifies me. wouldn't
use Bob Mills. But as you watch
this, think about what would
happen if you forget the where
statement. Be back in a second.
Oh
yeah, I used to have blonde hair.
I'll have to update my database.
Update Mills,
set hair color equal to blonde,
where, name equal Bob Mills.
And then my hair turned brown and I
have to update the database update
mills set hair color equal to
brown where name equals Bob Mills
now it's turning gray set hair color
equal to gray where name equals
Bob Mills all right after that video
you can see there were the three
parts to it the update statement
the set statement and then the
where clause let's take a look at
what happens to our student table if
we only do update and we update
and then it's the name of the table
so in this case we're using the
student table and what we're thinking
here is Sam Hines wants to change
his major from MIS to analytics
and we know that is what Sam wants
to do. However, if we run this,
81 rows affect it, it looks
like it worked out okay. We run
the select statement, and now
everybody is analytics. Yikes!
Now sometimes you do want to use all
columns to be changed. For instance,
we could look this up, but we want
everything to be uppercase in,
let's say, the major column. So we
can have where major is equal to,
and in this case we
could indicate using the
upper function and we
indicate their major.
81 rows affected and now you
can see that every row has been
changed. So when we do data
wrangling and data cleansing we may
want every row to be affected.
And that's the update without
having a WHERE clause. All
right, let's say SAM changes back
to MIS. In this case we could
indicate WHERE setMajor is equal
to MIS, and now SAM will be
the only major, but at this
time we do remember and
where student ID equal to 1.
So update is a powerful tool
to make changes to your tables,
but remember without the where
clause everything changes, and
most of the time that's not what
you want to occur. And the delete
statement is also dangerous,
just like the update statement.
For delete, we would indicate,
and delete is considered DML because
you typically are only removing
a row or a few rows. If you
want to get rid of all the rows,
remember, you can use truncate,
which removes the rows and keeps the
database structure, the table
structure. You can also use drop
table, and those are considered
DML because the entire table is
effective. In this case, we would
indicate delete from student. If I
run this, it will remove all
students. A test question could be,
is delete from student similar to
the truncate student table? And
the answer would be yes. They
effectively would do the same thing.
Also related to the delete statement
is a reminder about referential
integrity and some of the concepts
that we discussed earlier.
For instance, if we want to
get rid of Sam, you're out of
here, Sam. we would indicate
delete from student where
student ID, if I can spell it,
is equal to, and SAM is one.
If I run this code, we
want to get rid of SAM, but
we can't. It says the delete
statement is conflicted
with the reference and
the student activity,
and SAM is referenced in a
few different tables. So as a
reminder, we would have to drop,
delete the child rows, Sam and
the other tables, the child
tables, before we can delete them
here. And the idea is we don't
want to have Sam somewhere in
the database if he is not even
in the main one as a student.
For alter table, we're only going
to use two different commands. One
is to add a column, and the other
alter table is to remove a column.
All right, let's take a
look at our student table.
and in this case we're thinking we
want to add something like phone
number and in that case as a designer
you would ask yourself thinking of
normalization am I just going to have
one number or will I have multiple
numbers if it's multiple numbers we
know we have to create a separate
table if it's just one number we're
okay favorite number and you're
only allowed one favorite number
could this go on the table and the
answer is yes so let's go ahead and
add a column called favorite number.
Now, to do that, we'll write alter
table and the name of the table.
And this is considered a DDL
because we're altering the entire
structure we're adding or deleting a
column. And in this case, I'm going
to add, and I want to write the
word column, but you only do that
with a drop column. So when you're
preparing for the coding questions,
the alter table is fairly
consistent except for add and drop
are different. In this case, what
you would indicate is the name of
the column after add, the name of
the column that you want to add.
Let's indicate favorite number.
And then we indicate the
data type for that favorite
number. And in this
case, I'll just put int.
You may be thinking, if I'm adding a
column and the data type is integer,
should I also include other
information, for instance, null or not
null? Well, as you know, if I'm
gonna add a column, it will have null
values, and so in that case, by default,
it has to allow for null values.
Otherwise, the code
wouldn't run after the fact.
So we execute this, and we now
go and look at our data set,
and now we have a lot of
null numbers for our favorite
number, but again, that's
because we haven't added anything
to the data set. And now we
could go in doing update again.
Let's go ahead and add that.
Update.
The name of the table,
student, set, set favorite
number equal to 10. That was my
daughter's basketball number.
So we'll set it there. If we run
this, you know the problem,
right? We need that where clause.
But in this case, well, it's too late.
In the next class, we'll discuss
how to roll back our data sets.
Here now, everybody's favorite
number is 10. Now we don't like
that column. We want to get rid
of the favorite number. It doesn't
really make sense It's illegal
to track for some reason, so we
want to go in and change that
you'll note it in fact Let me keep
the date the alter table add
here, and I just want below that
alter table and now
we're going to drop and
We do write the name
column and then just the
name of the column without
using the data type
and this should run and now we've
removed that column so prior to
taking the exam you'll definitely
want to go through and make sure
that you're proficient on writing
code creating a table dropping a
table truncating a table insert
into alter table update and delete
we're also at a stage in the course
where the ben gone book becomes
relevant if you're interested
in using it To be successful in
class, you can certainly do it with
the video demonstration lectures,
the PowerPoint slides that
are associated with that, the
animation, and the labs project.
So you can do well there. But
for those of you who want to
take it one step further, it's
this part of the course where
you can start to use the Ben
Ghosn book that I highly recommend.
And if it's available for
free, there's an announcement
that will be made for that.
Ben Ghosn has only about three
pages on the update statement. It
has everything that we've covered
for this particular class,
so update using the where clause,
but it has a small section on
update based on a join. How do
you do an update based on a join?
And then it has a few related topics
that we don't cover in 5300, for
instance, merging data. And so I
would highly recommend for those that
are motivated that have a passion
for SQL is to start to use the Ben
-Gon book to complement the current
instruction that is provided online.
And now I recommend that you watch
the nightclub SQL simulation.
In this case, Randy and Sandy
control the entire world using
OLTP. I hope you enjoy that,
and I hope that it helps to
reinforce the concepts that
we're learning as well. So the
course is set up to help
complement those different learning
styles. So we have the
traditional lecture demonstration.
Along with that, you have
the labs to reinforce that.
And then you have the animations,
which is a different modality
that hopefully will help you
remember the concept longer term.
And then finally, for some of
you, the Ben-Gon book is a great
supplement to help round out your
knowledge of a particular topic.
The culminating project for this
module is the SQL internship,
Soda or Pop. We're doing a
simple study to determine
whether you say pop or soda.
I'm from Montana, and so
I tend to say POP, but it
varies based on your states.
And for this, we will cover briefly
normalization, ER diagramming,
your DDLDML, altering tables,
updating, and deleting different
information. So here are the project
goals that are also described
under the project design. But in
order to complete this particular
task, you'll be using OLTP in order
to solve this particular project
and get the data clean and ready
to go to analyze for the study.
Best of luck to you as you
learn. Get down with OLTP, and we
will see you for the exam review.
Have a great day. Take care.
Yeah, SQL Online Transaction
Processing. Who's down?
You down with OLTP?
you down with OLTP you down with OLTP
who's down with OLTP